back and today we are going to do
distributed shoulduling. Okay. So we
will not just cover watering we will
also go one level deep like how it works
internally. So it's going to be very
interesting. So let's not waste more
time and start it with like what is
scheduuler. Okay. So in very simple term
if you have to describe we can say
scheduleuler is nothing but a background
thread that sleeps until a given time.
Wake up perform a task and sleep again.
Okay. So this is the most simplistic
definition we can say about scheduleuler
and spring boot does not perform any
magic. Okay. Internally it just make use
of scheduled threadpool executor.
So if you remember from the Java series
in Java series we have covered thread
pool and threadpool executor and also
scheduled threadpool exeutor. So spring
boot internally make use of scheduled
threadpool exeutor itself.
Okay. So we have to understand this very
like how actually this works. If we
understand this spring boot in spring
boot how we performuling how
distributeduling works that is like
like it's like uh wrapper around this uh
schedule thread pool executor okay so I
would say that the prerequisite is that
you know what is threadpool and what is
threadpull executor schedule threadpool
executor I will go one again here in
more depth
And uh but at least
this is I would say that it's a
prerequisite like what is thread pool
executor when we create a thread pool
executor object what happens like it
create a queue it create a pool of
worker threads how the task is picked
and so at least basic we need to know
what's the flow of the thread pool and
thread pool executor
okay so with that said I would start
with like on this part schedule
threadpull executor part.
Now let's say that the first thing
generally what we do is we create a
threadpull exeutor. So in case of
scheduleuler so see we are dealing with
scheduleuler means something it's a
background thread and
it generally sleeps when task comes in a
queue.
task comes in a queue, the thread
wakes up, pick the task from the queue,
perform it and then sleeps again. Okay,
for this specific scenario, scheduleuler
scenario,
we have one specialized threadpool
exeutor which is scheduled thread pool
executor.
Okay. So here in this one first the step
what we are doing is we are creating an
object of it and with the parameter
three what does this three means
in the pool
we now have three worker thread.
So it's a core pool size. If you
remember from the thread pool and thread
pool executor the term you might be
familiar with core pool size that is
nothing but like okay in a pool how many
worker threads are present which take
care of a particular queue in which the
task will arrive.
Okay. The second generally what we used
to do is like the creating the task
which we have to run. So this is just a
runnable task and this is just a lambda
expression.
Okay, where I have specified the task
which has to be performed nothing much.
The third is we need to submit the task.
Okay, so we need to submit the task into
the queue. How we submit? So the
scheduleuler thread pool executor
dot we are using its object dot schedule
the task the task which we have to run.
So we have created the task and at what
time. So that's what actually
additional feature of schedule
threadpool executor. We can tell the
time the task need to run. In a normal
thread pool executor this feature is not
available. You can say that okay when we
put a task into the queue if thread is
available it will pick the task. But we
have a scenario like we have to run a
task at a specific time. Then it is like
scheduled threadful executor we have to
use. Okay. So executor dot schedule I am
using a schedule method the task which I
need to run and also I add the time at
what time this task need to get
scheduled. Okay. So what happen is this
task is get added to the queue. Okay.
And the worker thread which we have
created the pool of worker thread one of
the thread wakes up
pick the task on this specific time.
Okay, very important. On a specific time
when the time has come for this task to
run only that time
it will take out from the queue
perform
perform the task and then sleeps again.
So this is you can say that very very
high level but now we have to go one
level deep.
So,
so before we proceed further into the
internals like what happens when we
write this command, what happens when we
do dot schedule, what happen internally.
I will also cover that apart from dot
schedule like what are the other methods
and what their mean is because see we
have already covered those into this
Java schedule threadpull executor but I
will also cover here because you can say
that these are the fundamental if we
know how this methods work schedule at
fixed rate
schedule with fixed delay okay then it
will help us to understand the internal
better. Okay. So let's cover those
quickly.
The first method which schedule
threadpool executor providers is
schedule method. Okay. So here we have
runnable which is nothing but a task and
the delay and the unit let's say 5
second 10 seconds. So after how much
delay we need to run this task that's
what it say. So run only once
delay is counted from task submission
time. So here for example I am running
this executor dot schedule
the task which I want to run and after
this much delay okay 5 seconds. So now
let's say this is a time series and at
this point of time I have submitted my
task submitted the task.
Okay, I have done dot schedule and when
we when you do dot schedule it insert
submit your task to the queue. Okay, now
what happen is it wait for 5 seconds
1 2 3 4 5 and after 5 seconds your task
will get start. So that's what it mean
how we will see that don't worry about
that how after 5 seconds it able how it
able to schedule it. So shoulduling part
how it's working we will see internally
how it works but for now my intention is
that this methods behavior should be
clarified. Okay so schedule is clear run
only once and delay is counted from task
submission time when the task is
submitted after that your timer you can
say that starts and this much time once
elapsed your task get started.
Another is schedule at fixed rate.
So parameters are runnable which is
nothing but a task
initial delay. So see scheduled at fixed
rate means it repeated many times. Okay.
So initial delay means the first
the first task when it should be picked.
So after that uh so initial delay so
initial delay should be there after that
only first task should be picked. Okay
after that what should be the delay gap
between each repetition. So that's what
we say period time unit. So let's
understand with an example. So schedule
at fixed rate says that run the task
repeatedly at a fixed rate.
Example is let's say you are giving you
are performing this operation executor
dot schedule at fixed rate the task
which you want to run
initial delay you put two and after that
the period you have put four and the
time unit is second 4 secondond gap
after that you want it. So now let's say
this is the timeline and at this point
of time we have submitted the task. Now
what happen is what we have given
initial delay is 2 seconds. So it will
wait 2 seconds 1 2. So the first time it
will picked after the initial delay. So
the the task get picked up at 2 seconds
your task is started. Okay.
Okay. Now let's say task is finished.
What is the next time? because it has to
be the same task need to be put into the
queue.
Okay. So let me also cover one more
thing.
Let's say you have put a task.
Okay. And we are working on this fixed
rate. So it has to be repeated multiple
times. So now let's say thread one.
Thread one pick this task to run.
This is the task
which thread one is picked. Okay. At 2
second. Let's say at this point of time
it picked 2 second.
Now after this task is executed
successfully
since we are following schedule at fixed
rate means it has to be repeated again
after this
after this much gap after this much
delay. Okay. So the same task the same
task see object that's why I'm uh
focusing here is the same task object is
same
okay so the same object with
new execution time
is again put back into the que
okay and I will tell you what Q is there
when we go internally like howululing
works. But here why I stopped there and
focus is that see for each task you have
only one object.
Okay. So when the task successfully
computed then only it would be if if it
need to be repeat again only after its
execution
it has to be put again with new
execution time back into the queue.
Okay. So now come this come to this
example again.
So initial delay was 2 seconds. So this
is the time when the task was submitted.
Okay. So this is the time when it is
submitted. Wait for 2 seconds. Task got
picked up. Now let's say that uh what is
the next execution time you need to
compute. So now task is finished. We
need to compute the next execution time
because so that we have to put back into
the queue. So here at fixed rate the
formula is that previous start time plus
delay. What is the previous start time?
Previous start time is 2 seconds. So 2
plus what is the delay? We have given 4
second.
So next execution time is six. So this
task is put back again into the queue
with the execution. Next execution time
is 6 second. On the 6th second this
should get executed.
Now when the 6th second arrive
some thread would pick it up. Task
started and when task get finished
since we are following fixed rate we
need to put it back again into the
queue. And for that we need to compute
the new execution time. And to compute
the new execution time what is the
formula for fixed rate? Previous
Start time
plus delay. What is the previous start
time here? The previous start time here
was 6 second. It was started, right? 6
plus the delay we have provided is 4
second.
Now the next
run. So we have put back this task again
into the queue with the execution time
as 10 second. So at 10 second some
thread will pick it up. So at 10 second
some thread will pick it up and after it
finish the task now can you tell it need
to compute the next execution time
again. So previous runtime previous
runtime was 10. The delay is we have
provided is four. So it's a 14. So now
the next run would be like on the 14
second and so on. Keep on doing keep on
doing keep on doing.
Now here interview can ask you one
critical question.
What if task takes too much time? What
if the task which you have submitted
here at picked at this point 2 second?
What if it is still running? What
happened to this? At 6 it should get
picked up. At 10 it should get picked
up. Okay. So generally most engineer
what uh in interview they get confused
that they say that it might run in
parallel. Okay this is executed at 2
seconds. So they will compute the next
delay previous runtime two. The delay
time we have said is four. So at six
also it will get executed. No, that's
why I previously told you we have only
one task object
and when this task object is completed
finished the same task object put back
into the queue with new execution time.
Okay. So there is no way the same task
can run parallel because we have only
one task object itself and the same task
object we put into the queue after
completion.
So what our answer is even if task takes
too much time it will always run in
sequential manner. Why? Because same
task object is recued.
Let's understand this with an example.
So again the same example I'm picking
schedule at fixed rate the task which I
want to submit
two which is an initial delay
after that what would be the subsequent
delay I wanted
so initial delay is 2 seconds so at two
let's say started from zero at two the
task started so first task started at
two now let's say at 12 second this task
got finished at 12 seconds this task get
finished.
So now we need to compute. So I told you
after after the task is finished we
compute a new execution time. Okay. So
at 12 secondond task is finished now we
are going to compute the new execution
time. So how we compute in the
schedule at fixed rate scenario. So what
it will do formula is previous start
time plus fixed delay time. Previous
start time was 2. 2 + delay is
4 second.
So 6 second. So next execution I is 6.
But see we are already at 12. So 6
second is past. So again compute the
new.
So 6 second is less than current 12
seconds. So this is like we need to find
a new time. This is a history. So 6
second the next execution time we
compute is like 6 second + 4. What
should be the next? It generally it
should be 10 second. It should run. Must
10 second is also passed. We are
currently at 12 second. So it will try
to compute the next.
So previous execution would should be 10
+ 4 delay 14 second. So now 14 second is
future current is 12 second. So the next
run would happen on port 10.
So it will put the task.
So it will put the task back into the
queue with the execution
time is 14 second.
Okay. So the task again will run on 14
second.
So this is clear. scheduled at fixed
rate.
Now we have schedule with fixed delay.
Okay, there is a very minor difference.
Okay, so here also we run the task
repeatedly but with fixed delay. Fixed
delay very simple to understand in this
case the understand this with an
example. schedule with fixed delay the
task which we want to schedule initial
delay and after that how much delay we
wanted within a uh within two run. So
initial delay is 2 seconds. So if you
see the timeline let's say at zero uh
our task is submitted. So at two the
task should get started.
Okay. So at 2 seconds because of initial
delay. So this much time it waited and
after that task started. Now here
now now let's say that task is finished
at 12 seconds. Task is finished at 12
seconds.
The new runtime
is computed here in schedule with fixed
delay is previous finish time plus
delay.
That's the only difference. Earlier in
the fixed uh this one fixed rate, the
formula is previous start time plus
delay. Here is previous finish time plus
delay. So when it is finished on 12 plus
what is the delay? 4 second. So next run
would be 16 second. Okay. So at 16
second the next run would get started
because first run started on 2cond but
task finished on 12 second. Okay. So the
next execution time it will compute 12
second + 4 when the time is when the
task is finished. After that it will add
up the delay.
Okay. So 16 second is the time. Then
let's say it is finished on 18 second.
So we need to find the next run. Then
only we have to put back into the queue.
So when it is finished 18 + 4 22 second.
So the task is put back into the queue
with this new execution time 80 uh 22
seconds. So 22 seconds task started and
so on. So you got the difference in the
fixed delay when the task started and
when the task finished. So using this
time when it is finished we add a delay
and get a new execution time and then it
again put back to the queue and in the
fixed rate
when the task was started in that we put
a delay
if it is future
then only we put back into the queue.
You can say that
okay
future in the sense I would say that uh
greater than equals to now. So even
though it is equals to then also it will
uh we can put it into the queue because
it can be executed. Okay
but this is clear right.
So now with that being said
let's see what happened
when we perform this command. So when we
did scheduleuler threadpull executor
we create its object
and pass this parameter three. So what
ultimately we are doing is we are create
passing this as a core pool size
and what it does is
it created a thread pool with three
worker thread.
Okay. And since we are using scheduled
thread pool executor the queue which it
uses delayed work q. Delayed workq.
Okay. You can also say delayed Q also.
So it internally follows min heap sorted
by time and it this Q is unbounded grow
as needed and limited by available heap
memory.
Okay. So when you perform the first like
new schedule thread pool executor 3 this
all thing happen. So we have created a
delayed work q which is of unbounded
size which keep on grow and get filled
and it's a min heap. So when the task
come the task should have a time and
based on the time it is sorted
internally. So it's a min heap. So the
task which need to be run immediately is
on the head of the queue. You can say
that and also it creates a pool with the
worker number which you have specified
into this parameter.
Okay.
Now after that what we used to do we
used to create a task. Let's say this is
our task nothing. And the third one
which is important is schedule it. So
nowuling
it. executor dot schedule
task this one. So we need to schedule
this task after this much time. So what
it does?
So internally first thing it will create
it schedule task. So from this task it
will create one you can say that
schedule
future task
and this has uh this task plus this time
unit information 5 seconds.
Okay.
So that is one task you can say that
that is one schedule task which
ultimately goes into the queue.
So now when you put dot schedule what it
does is it also insert it into the
delayed work also. Okay. So it also
insert the task for first it create a
schedule future task object and uh you
can say that wrap it up this task plus
this time information and that object is
now inserted into the delayed work.
So
now let's go one level deep again
how the flow happens like when you
insert into the delayed cube what
exactly happens.
So
the first is not optimized flow. Here
also it's a very important interview
question. One is nonoptimized flow.
Another is optimized which is a leader
follower flow. Okay, this is where many
interviewer uh start with this and then
they ask the follow-up to this leader
follower question. But let's see the
flow what happened. So at step one
delayed work q is empty and all the
worker threads are in weight state. So
if you remember from the thread pool
executor flow in Java uh each thread has
an state.
Okay. So initially when they created
they are created let's say in runnable
state
runnable state so it would be runnable
runnable runnable but since delayed
workq is empty
what they do is they goes into the
weight state so this is the framework
code so now here if you see the
framework code let me zoom it a bit
each thread so see this is an infinite
loop each thread And
let me change it to green so that would
be visible. Okay. So each thread
continuously loop. Okay. And they check
the head of the delayed queue. So if
there is no task present
they goes into the weight state
indefinitely until they are not get
woke up by somebody else. So they are in
weight state. So this is our step one.
So delayed Q is empty and all worker
threads are in weight state. So all
worker thread checking the Q head
currently it is null and they are
waiting. Okay. So now they goes into the
wait state. Somebody has to now wake
them up.
Step two the first tasks arrive in the
delayed queue. And how the first tasks
arrive in the delayed queue? We have
like executor
dot schedule or schedule at fixed rate
or schedule at with fixed delay. So we
have that command right this one it also
inserted into this delayed workq.
So when the first task arrive in the
delayed queue what exactly happened? It
invokes only one worker thread only one
worker thread which are in waiting
state. It will not invoke all three. It
will not do notify all. No, it will just
invoke one thread which is in waiting.
Okay. When the task comes into the
delayed work, it invoke only one. So
here this is the
code example here if you see offer. So
internally
when we do dot schedule it might be
calling this method of the delayed work
q offer and the task which we have to
insert. So here if you see what it do it
first
if the Q length has been full if there
is no space in the queue it will grow it
increase the size Q by 50% if it is full
and after that it will insert it and do
heify it will heify because since I told
you the delayed cues we are following
min heap
min heap based on the time so it will
heify and after that What it does is
if Q head equals to equals to this the
object the task which is coming means
this is the first task which is coming.
So earlier if the Q is empty all threads
thread one thread two thread three are
in weight
wait.
So if this is the first task if the head
is this is the task means all thread
might be in waiting state because this
is the first thread coming first task
coming so that's why it is doing signal
signal is equivalent to you can say that
notify which only randomly invokes one
thread which is in waiting state. It do
notify all it randomly pick one thread
and notify it invoke it.
Okay. So this is the step two which
happens.
Now step three. In the step three, now
we have a worker thread which got now in
runnable state. We have a task in the
delayed que. What it do is
it check the queue again because I told
you right it continuously in the for
loop and checking the head of the que
and why we need to check the head of the
queue because it's a min heap and min
heap you know that at the head stores
the let's say if you are following a
minimum heap on time at head we have the
time which going to be come immediately
or already has come you can say that so
the task which need to be run
immediately that would be at the head of
the queue. Okay.
So now this worker will look at the head
of the queue. Worker one check the head
of the head task.
So now we have two possibility. What is
the two possibility? Possibility one the
current time greater than equals to task
one runtime.
Okay. So means this time is already
elapsed. So current time is let's say
210 and the task which is present here
in the queue is 2. So definitely it need
to be picked if time is already elapsed.
So what it will do is it will take out
the task from the que and start working
on it. Okay. The similar that if the
current time is 2011
and in the Q we have two. So yes time is
already elapsed for this task. So this
worker
start working on this task one and state
is now running. Earlier it was runnable.
Now it is working on task one. It status
is now running.
What is the possibility two? So this is
the possibility one. Possibility two is
that
so currently is let's say 155
but this task needs to be executed at 2.
So time has not yet come. So possibility
two is that current time is less than
task one runtime.
So we need to compute the delay. So it
will compute delay. How much time I need
to wait? So task one runtime 2 minus
what is the current time? Let's say 25.
So five either seconds or minute
whatever would be. So it has to wait
this much time. Let's say 5 seconds or 5
minutes whatever. So difference is like
what's the time the task need to run
what's the current time whatever the
difference this much time this thread
need to wait
now how this should wait one is like
let's say busy wait it will keep on
checking the clock hey is it now ready
is it now ready is it now ready is it
now ready and as soon as it ready take
it out that that is like you are
consuming many CPU CPU cycles it keep on
checking the queue. Are you ready now?
Are you ready now? Are you ready now?
Okay. So you are consuming CPU cycles.
Okay. So we are saying that
we don't do busy wait. So this whatever
the 5 minutes or 5 seconds this thread
has to wait. We don't have to busy wait.
We don't have to keep on continuously
looking and we don't have to consume the
CPU cycle. So what it do is it timed
weight. Time wait means JVM pass the
thread. Okay. And it will this thread
let's say thread one need to wait for 5
second. So it will goes into timed
wait state. So see there are two type of
state. One is wait state means threads
are in waiting indefinitely like what
our other threads are in. Until and
unless somebody don't invoke it, they
are waiting in wait state indefinitely.
They do not consume any CPU cycles.
Okay, they are not consuming any
resource. They are just in the wait
state. Somebody has to wake them up
indefinitely. They would be in wait
state. But here
here it goes to the timed wait state.
Time wait state means when we are saying
5 seconds. So it will go into the wait
state only for 5 seconds. As soon as 5
seconds are finished, it wakes up. Now
you might be asking that hey how it is
maintaining the timer that it internally
make use of OS level timer.
Okay. So
when the timer expires OS wakes the
thread and control returns to the JVM.
Okay. So OS keeps the timer and in the
OS uh there are certain functionality if
you read it they have certain thread
which keep every millisecond they check
any thread need to be wake up any thread
need to be wake up okay so OS has those
functionality OS has uh OS level timers
are present which itself they have a
thread which keep on checking every
millisecond that is there any thread
which I need to wake up or not okay so
they keep the timer and when the timer
of this time weight threads which are
time weight with this much time when
that timer is over OS thread wake them
up and return control return back to JVM
so understand with this let's say
current time is 1:55 p.m. Delay time is
2 p.m. So 5 minute it has to wait. Okay.
So this worker thread will not
continuously
look at this. Hey time is it is time
come time come or not. What it goes into
time wait for 5 minutes. Now OS will
keep the timer. Okay. And OS will wake
it up after 5 minutes are over. And once
it is over what it will do is it will
then check the queue back again. It will
start again the same process.
So here if you see
this is the for loop where each thread
continuously
keep on iterating iterating iterating.
Currently our thread two and thread
three are in the weight state here. Now
thread one
here
it perform this for loop. Yes.
Now it will check the head of the cube.
Is it null? No. It goes here. Compute
the delay. So two possibility. First
possibility delay is finished less than
equals to zero.
So if delay is over like it can be
executed immediately. So it finish the
poll. So what it will do is
poll is it take out from the queue and
start executing it.
And this is the second possibility. If
the delay is still greater than zero
means there is still some time left
before it task can get executed. So what
it does is it goes into the weight
state.
Now here if you see it's not going await
it's going await nanos and the time. So
it going into the timed weight state for
a specific time only whatever the delay
we have calculated okay 5 minutes is
still pending. So that much time it will
go into the
weight state.
Okay, don't worry about this leader and
all. We will put that into the optimized
flow. What does that mean? But here we
know that two possibilities are clear.
What happen in this one if the timer is
not completed?
Now after the time weight state is over,
I told you that worker one threads wake
up again here. It will wake up from here
again and what it will do? It will again
start this for loop. Again this for loop
will start. It will check the queue
again. It will check the head of the
queue again. Do we have a task? Yes, we
have a task. Okay, it will compute the
delay. Now the delay is over because it
has already sleep for that much time.
Now what it will do is delay is less
than equals to this. It will finish it.
Okay, it will take out the task from the
queue and per start working on it.
Now one question might have comes to our
mind
when the task one
which is there in the delayed queue is
got picked by the worker one okay which
was uh like in the wake state okay which
was wake up now it is running
who is looking into the delayed work
what if there are more task come okay
what if or you can say that what if
apart from task one there is also task
true.
Okay.
from the previous offer flow like when
the task comes into the
queue where it was uh
this one offer in the offer flow when it
invoked the one thread when
when there is only one task into the
delayed queue because all might be into
the uh all threads might be into wait
state. So the first task come then only
it notify but if there are more task it
do not notify. So the question is
my question is
let's say we have task one task two task
three we have more than one task okay
and this was the this was earlier
uh await
waiting timed
timed waiting
for 5 minutes after this 5 minutes are
over this thread come into runnable
state
in the runnable state. It checked the
queue again. Now the time is over for
this task. So it picked this task. It
removed this task and start processing
it. Now it's uh state is in running.
Now who will look this delayed work q?
Who will look this delayed workq?
because during the offer it only invoke
one thread when when only one task is
present into the queue. Okay. But now
since there are more than one thread, it
will not call notify or signal. Now who
will look? These threads are in wait and
we have more task. What would happen?
So here if you see there is one finally
block.
So when the thread
goes to take out the task from the Q
delayed Q to start working on it, it
will check into the finally block before
returning. It will in the finally block
will get execute. If Q is not null, it
has some data present invoke one more
thread which is in waiting. Okay. So you
can say that
if I
clean it a bit. Uh but here it is. Uh
here just a sec. Let me clean it a bit.
Huh?
So now when this worker goes into the
running state performing some task if
there is more task into the queue
it invokes one more worker let's say
worker three or randomly it goes into
runnable state
okay so that question might also comes
up
so this is just about explain now one
thread which was awake is now going to
process the task task. But what if the
but if it process the task then no one
will be looking at the delay Q and if
there is more task in the delay queue it
will invoke notify one more thread which
is in waiting state that's what so let's
say task two is already present task one
is picked task two is also present so in
the finally block
uh head is not null it will invoke
one more thread which is in waiting
Okay.
And the process keeps going on. I told
you this is an infinite loop and the
process keeps going on and on and on.
Clear? Now you might ask, hey why I
mentioned it's not optimized? It's all
look optimized. So all well and good.
Okay. I I am able to understand how the
task is inserted into the delayed queue.
how the threads wd up only one thread
wked up and if the uh since it's a mean
hip the head is store the task which
need to be run immediately
and uh the thread picks up the task if
the time is not over it goes into time
weight state and when the timer is
completed it wakes up now and pick the
task so all well and good where is it is
not optimized
See this below use case let's say
current time is two and this is our
delay Q task one two task 2 2 task 3 2
p.m. and task four let's say four
thread one okay so currently thread one
is in runnable state let's say this is
our current scenario okay the same
scenario which we have covered right
it was in runnable state and we have a
task present here
so what would happen thread one runnable
state checks the head of the que
hey task one is ready to be picked
Yes, current time is two, task one is
two. So what it will do is it will
remove the task one and before it going
to process it, it also invoke one more
waiting thread to look at the cube. I
told you already that before it
so
this is the take. So there is before it
pull before it take out the task from
the queue it also check in the finally
block if the head is not empty invoke
one more okay so what it will do task
one
is now handled by thread one okay and it
also invoked
another thread which is in waiting and
thread one goes into the waiting state
or running state it is performing task
one.
Thread two now goes into the runnable
state. Okay. Now thread two goes into
the runnable state. Why? Because thread
one invokes randomly. Now let's say that
randomly thread two got picked up. Now
it will again check the head of the
queue. Task two is ready to be picked.
Yes, the current time is two and this is
two. So it will remove the task two and
before it going to process it the code
is same. It will invoke one more thread
which is in waiting state because the
que is not empty. Okay. So thread two
goes into the running state but it will
invoke one randomly one more thread
which is in waiting. So now thread two
got waked up in runnable state. Thread
two is in running state. It is
performing task two.
Okay. So task two is also removed.
Now thread three check the head of the
queue.
Task three is ready to be picked. Yes,
two. Current time is also two. So it
remove the task three. And before it
going to process it, it also tried to
invoke one more waiting thread to look
at the queue. But since there are no
more thread in the queue, they are all
busy. So assume we have only three
threads, three worker thread into the
pool. So currently all three threads are
in running state processing task one,
task two and task three.
Okay. And in the queue we have only now
left is task four. So this is our
current state. Now in the queue we have
task four which need to be done at 4.
Current time is 2 p.m. let's say. And
all the workers are running. Worker one
running task one. Worker two running
task uh two. Worker three running task
three.
Now at three all three workers thread
finished their task. Finished finish.
Now once they finish they again goes
back to runnable state. Okay. So it goes
back to runnable. Runnable runnable. Now
all three will complete
this delayed que for the task because
it's just a for loop right all three
tasks are running parallelly. It's a for
loop. So they will compete. So here if
you look at the code of the take so they
all compete for this uh delayed queue
and they will try to take a lock. Okay,
they will try to take a lock. Whichever
takes a lock first will pick the task
from the queue.
Now all three compete for the task.
Now let's say that thread one acquired
the lock first. Okay, thread one or
worker one. Worker thread one acquired
the lock first. What would happen now?
You know the flow. What it will do is it
will check only two possibility. Either
time expired. So current time is three.
We have said that current time is three.
Now so either time is expired, not
expired. So in this case it is not
expired. So current is three but it need
to be executed at four. So what it will
do is it will compute the delay delay
time 4 - 3 1 let's say it's a minute all
we are doing in minute let's say 1
minute it will go into timed weight
state
it will go into time weight state for 1
minute
now once it goes into a timed weight
state so it will also release the lock
also now once it release the lock the
second thread acquire the lock again do
the same thing again currently it's
three it's four it also goes into the
time weight. Similarly, now after it
before it thread two goes into the time
weight, it will release the lock. Thread
three will take it and the same thing
this will also go into the time weight.
So now here if you see all three goes
into the time weight state. Now OS has
to keep a timer for all these three.
Okay. So why unnecessarily all three
goes into the time waiting? The the more
optimized solution is that only one
thread only one thread should goes into
the timed weight state
other two threads should goes into
weight state indefinitely one. We have
already seen that flow. Okay. So that's
our expectation. But because of this use
case all three goes into the time
waiting state. So that's where our
optimized flow comes into the picture.
Leader follower pattern or leader
follower optimization comes into the
picture. So very basic idea of leader
follower is it's very very simple like
many times it get complicated. I'm not
sure like but it's very simple. It's
only agenda is only agenda is only one
thread should go into time waiting. All
others should just go waiting state
indefinitely.
OS should maintain the timer only for
one thread in case of delete Q.
Okay.
And it's all managed through one
variable itself leader variable. Now you
will understand with this flow example.
So step one again I am following the
same step. Okay. So you can skip step
one, step two. You can directly jump to
step three. But I'm going little slow
because this is fundamental this asked a
lot and it's just out of curiosity like
it should be understood properly. So I'm
going little slow. Please bear with me
or you can uh increase the speed.
Step one no change. So you know that
step one what is the case? Delayed Q was
empty and all workers are in weight
state and currently now we have a leader
object which is in null currently.
Step two again no change. In step two,
first task arrive in the delayed queue.
And when the first task arrive, you know
that what it do? It will also notify
one
thread. Okay? Only for the first time
the task comes into the delayed queue.
Okay? Or not only the first time, only
when there is one task, only when there
is one task in the delayed queue, then
only it notify because when there is no
task, all might be in waiting state. So
when the first time task come it need to
invoke one.
Okay. So it invoke one thread which are
in waiting state. Now let's say worker
one goes into the runnable state. Leader
is still null. No change how we used to
do in the previous. Step three. Step
three worker one
look at the head of the delayed queue.
Two possibility. Possibility one no
change. Okay. Now let's say current time
is 2011. But in the delayed queue the
task need to be run at 2. Yeah. Uh it's
already expired. It need to get
executed. It will take it out and start
processing. And since currently there is
no task present into the queue. So it
will not uh awake. If there is more task
present it will invoke it another. Okay.
So there is no change into the
possibility one scenario.
Okay. So this is the possibility one
scenario we have already seen
at this point of it some time leader is
null.
Okay. So no change at all.
Now possibility two. This is where the
leader variable comes [snorts] into the
work because this is the time when
thread goes into time
weight state.
Okay. So now understand this. So now
let's say current time is less than task
one runtime. So we compute a delay that
okay for let's say 5 seconds or 5
minutes still we need to wait. So now
what it does it it will check if leader
variable is not null means there is
already some leader
just go into the weight state because
here what we are building is only leader
should goes into timed weight state. All
those who are not leader should goes
into weight state.
Okay. So we have one condition if leader
variable is not null goes into the
weight state because leader might be
goes into the time weight. Else if there
is no leader make yourself leader and
goes into the time weight state and once
you once your timer is up make leader
equals to null again. So see all leader
variable is just to make sure that only
one thread goes into time wait state.
Okay. And all other thread if they need
to wait goes into wait indefinitely one
not the timer one. So here if you see
this one
all are in runnable state. I am just
reusing the same example use case where
we have the problem. All are runnable.
Leader is still null and we have this
task present into the delayed work. Now
all will
compete. Okay. And now let's say that
current time is three. So thread one
let's say acquire the log first. Thread
one will go checks the runtime is not
yet expired. Compute the delay. Let's
say delay is 1 minute.
Now it will check leader is null. Yes,
leader is null. So what it will do is it
make itself leader. Leader equals to
thread dot current thread. So now what's
the leader is leader is now worker one.
And then it goes into the timed waiting
state.
Okay. So it just set the leader that hey
I am the leader. I am going the time
working state. If after me if anybody
comes they don't have to go into the
time waiting state. So if you see the
code this is the code like if delay is
not over if delay is not over what it
does is leader not equals to null
currently we have a scenario where
leader was null. So when leader is null
the thread make itself leader. Okay so
here leader equals to this thread. So it
make itself leader and then goes into
the timed waiting state.
Okay. So now we have this scenario. Task
is still present. Worker one goes into
the time waiting state. Leader is now
worker one. Now it when it goes into the
time waiting state, it will release the
lock. Now the lock is taken by another
thread. Let's say thread two acquired
the lock. Checks the runtime it's four.
Current time is three. Delay is not yet
over. So it delay it computes. I need to
wait 1 minute. Okay. After that it check
leader not equals to null. Yes,
currently leader is our worker one. So
what it will do is it will directly goes
into weight state. That's our code is if
leader not equal goes into weight state
not for a specific time goes into
indefinitely.
Okay. So it goes into weight state. This
part leader not equal this. Similarly
while goes into the waiting it will
release the log. Now the thread three
comes again check the head. Uh compute
the delay. If delay is not yet over
still 1 minute left it need to wait. So
it will check leader is null. No leader
is already present. So it goes into the
wait state also.
Okay.
So now what would happen after 4 p.m.
After four, after 1 minute, after 1
minute
the timer is over, OS thread will make
this thread up. It wakes up. So at four,
worker thread one wakes up. After 1
minute delay, this get wake up. And
again it check the Q. Now current time
is four. This is four. So it's delay is
delay is greater uh delay is less than
equals to zero. Right? Delay is less
than equals to Z. True. Now it will
finish the pole. Okay. So what that's
what it does. But here if you see
before so here we see that at this point
of time
this worker one goes into
time weight state.
Okay. So when it wake up so it will
process it from here itself. So what it
does is if leader equals to equals to
thread a if I am the leader make leader
null. Okay. So it again make it null and
the process repeats. Process repeats. So
now we are in the same state. Leader is
null. Worker one is runnable. Okay. And
now it will look back at the que. Now
our delay time is less than equals to
zero. It will pick it up. It goes into
running state. Okay. for this task one.
If there are more tasks present
in the finally block leader is null.
Yes, leader is null. It will make and uh
there is some data present into the
queue. Yes, it will invoke another task,
another thread.
I hope it's clear like it's very
interesting like how it works and it's
asked a lot in interview but in high
level design also this has asked in
distributed microservices topics also it
is asked okay so sorry if it is a big
but kindly go through again if you find
it little bit uh here you if I go a
little fast okay so kindly check it out
again things will get clear for sure
Okay.
Okay. And if you have any doubt, let me
know. We can discuss further into the
comment section. Bye.